Register of the Juraj Slávik Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
- Speeches and Writings, 1933-1966. (Box 13-38)
  - Speech on the seizure of the Baltic states by international communism, 1954 December 19. (Folder 26: 27)
  - "Moja pamať - živá kniha," memoirs, volumes 4-9, published as a series in New Yorkský Denník, 1955-1957 (never as a book)., See also Microfilm (Box 27)
    - Typescript - Vol. 7, Vols. 8-9 ("Londýn 1940-1945: Government in exile"). (Folder 27: 1-5)
      Includes correspondence, radio broadcasts, and speeches
    - Typescript - Vol. 7, Vols. 8-9 ("Londýn 1940-1945: Government in exile"). (Box-folder 28: 1-4)
    - Typescript - Vol. 7, Vols. 8-9 ("Londýn 1940-1945: Government in exile"). (Box-folder 29: 1-5)
    - Typescript - Vol. 7, Vols. 8-9 ("Londýn 1940-1945: Government in exile"). (Box-folder 30: 1-5)
    - Typescript - Vol. 7, Vols. 8-9 ("Londýn 1940-1945: Government in exile"). (Folder 31: 1-4)
    - Printed copy
      - Vol. 4 - V diplomatickej službe vo Varšave, 1935-1939 (Box-folder 32: 1-5)
      - Vol. 4 - V diplomatickej službe vo Varšave, 1935-1939 (Box-folder 33: 1-2)
      - Vol. 5 - Moje poslanie vo Varšave II - Polsko-československý pomer v roku 1938 (Folder 33: 3-4)
      - Vol. 5 - Moje poslanie vo Varšave II - Polsko-československý pomer v roku 1938 (Box-folder 34: 1-4)
      - Vol. 6 - Príprava odboja v Amerike a v Polsku (Box-folder 35: 1-5)
      - Vol. 6 - Príprava odboja v Amerike a v Polsku (Box-folder 36: 1-3)
      - Vol. 7 - Národný výbor československý v Paríži (Oktober 1939 - Jun 1940) (Folder 36: 4-5)
      - Vol. 7 - Národný výbor československý v Paríži (Oktober 1939 - Jun 1940) (Box-folder 37: 1-4)
    - Reviews (Box-folder 38: 1)
  - Review of Jozef Lettrich, History of Modern Slovakia, 1955? (Folder 38: 2)
  - "Defamation of an Exile," comment on Kurt Glaser, Profile of an Exile Politician, 1955 January 15. (Folder 38: 3)
  - Speech, demonstration for free elections in Czechoslovakia, Chicago, Denní hlasatel, 1955 July 12. (Folder 38: 4)
  - Speech commemorating the 296th anniversary of Augustin Herman's coming to Maryland, Augustin Herman Czech American Historial Society, Baltimore, 1955 October 16. (Folder 38: 5)
  - Speech commemorating the 37th anniversary of the founding of the Czechoslovak Republic, 1955 October 28. (Folder 38: 6)
    Holograph and typescript (Slovak)
  - Letter to the editor, The Washington Post, 1956? January. (Folder 38: 7)
  - "Do nového roku," České slovo, 1956 January. (Folder 38: 8)
  - Speech commemorating the 20th anniversary of the Czechoslovak-American Center, Washington, D.C., 1957. (Folder 38: 9)
  - "Dr. Eduard Beneš," Naše Hlasy, 1957 June 1. (Folder 38: 10)
  - "O Dobronivskom kostole," New Yorkský Denník, 1957 July 17. (Folder 38: 11)
  - "Hubert Ripka zomrel," New Yorkský Denník, 1958 January 10. (Folder 38: 12)
  - "The Communist Coup in Czechoslovakia and the Free World," 1958 February 22. (Folder 38: 13)
  - "Odkaz T.G.M. a jeho syna Jana Masaryka," New Yorkský Denník, 1958 March 22. (Folder 38: 14)
  - Letter to the editor, The New York Herald Tribune, 1958 November 11. (Folder 38: 15)
  - "Uprchlický rok Spojených národov: Vianočná úvaha," 1959? (Folder 38: 16)
  - Speech commemorating Milan Rastislav Štefánik, 1959 May 3. (Folder 38: 17)
  - "Recent Cultural Developments in Czechoslovakia," 1959 December 8. (Folder 38: 18)
  - "Masaryk a Slovensko," Slovenský sokol, 1960 March 31. (Folder 38: 19)
  - "Milan Rastislav Štefánik," New Yorkský Denník, 1961 August 3. (Folder 38: 20)
  - Speech commemorating the 120th anniversary of the birthday of Antonín Dvořák, and the 43rd anniversary of Czechoslovak independence, Washington, D.C., 1961 October 28. (Folder 38: 21)
  - "Kronika kilku dní," note on Kazimierz Papee, 1962. (Folder 38: 22)
    Typescript (in Polish and Slovak)
  - "T. G. Masaryk," New Yorkský Denník, 1962 September 14. (Folder 38: 23)
    Typescript. Includes writings and speeches commemorating Tomáš Garrigue Masaryk on various occasions
  - Review of Ladislav Mňačko, Oneskorené reportáže, 1963?n.d. (Folder 38: 24)
  - Letter to the editor, The Washington Post, 1963 October 24. (Folder 38: 25)
  - Review of Alexander Werth, Russia at War, 1941-1945, 1964? (Folder 38: 26)
  - "Velvyslanec Lawrence A. Steinhardt o událostiach, ktoré predchádzaly komunistickému puču ve februári 1948," Proměny, 1964. (Folder 38: 27)
  - "Paul Reynaud a Československo," 1966. (Folder 38: 28)
  - Letters to the editor, 1966 March. (Folder 38: 29)
- Career File, 1936-1968. (Box 39-47)
  Articles, brochures, chronological records, correspondence, interviews, lists, memoranda, newsletters, notes, outlines, programs, reports, schedules, statements, study, survey, clippings, and miscellany relating to professional activities of Juraj Slávik, arranged chronologically by title of position
  - Ambassador to Poland, 1936 February - 1939 March
    - Appointment letter (Folder 39: 1)
    - Correspondence (Folder 39: 2-8)
    - Dispatches (Box 40)
      - 1934-1936 (Folder 40: 1)
      - 1937-1939 (Folder 40: 2)
    - Letters of credence (Folder 40: 3)
    - Notes by Slávik (Folder 40: 4)
    - Reports by Slávik and others to ZAMINI (Ministerstvo zahraničních věcí v Praze)
      - 1936 (Folder 40: 5-6)
      - 1937 (Box-folder 41: 1-2)
      - 1938 (Folder 41: 3-5)
      - 1938 (Box-folder 42: 1-2)
      - 1939 (Folder 42: 3-4)
    - Miscellaneous (Folder 42: 5)
  - Member, Czechoslovak National Committee (Československý Národní Výbor), 1939-1940 (Box-folder 43: 1)
  - Minister of the Interior, Government-in-Exile, State Council (Ministerská Rada), London, 1940-1945., See also Speeches and Writings/General/Transcripts of radio broadcasts/BBC
    - Correspondence (Folder 43: 2-3)
    - Reports (Folder 43: 4)
    - Miscellaneous (Folder 43: 5)
  - Minister of Education, Government-in-Exile, 1940-1945 (Folder 43: 6)
  - Minister of Foreign Affairs, Czechoslovakia, 1945 June -1946 June (Folder 43: 7)
  - Ambassador to the United States, 1946 June - 1948 March (Box 44)
    - Bulletins (Folder 44: 1)
    - Correspondence (Vlado Clementis, Edvard Beneš)., See also Subject file/Paris Peace Conference (Folder 44: 2)
    - Dispatches (Folder 44: 3)
    - Instructions of the Czechoslovak Ministry of the Interior, August 17, 1949, regarding visa obligations. (Folder 44: 4)
      Includes a list of persons whose visas to the United States were withheld
    - Letters of credence (Folder 44: 5)
    - List of persons who left Czechoslovakia after the coup d'état, 1948 (Folder 44: 6)
    - Subject file
      - Paris Peace Conference (1946).
        Includes transcripts of proceedings, summaries, speeches, and agenda, relating to the peace settlement at the end of World War II
        - Agreement between Czechoslovakia and Hungary regarding population transfers (Folder 44: 7-8)
        - Draft peace treaty with Hungary, 1946 (Folder 44: 9)
        - Notes by Slávik (Folder 44: 10)
      - Resignation. (Folder 44: 11)
        Includes press releases
      - Resignation. (Box-folder 45: 1-4)
    - Telegrams (Folder 45: 5)
    - Miscellaneous (Folder 45: 6)
  - Member of the Executive Board and Chairman of the Social-Aid Committee, Council of Free Czechoslovakia (U.S.), 1949
    - Circulars (Folder 45: 7)
    - Correspondence (Folder 45: 8)
    - Declarations, including of 1968 (Box-folder 46: 1)
    - Lists
      - Books (Folder 46: 2)
      - Members (Folder 46: 3)
      - Names (Folder 46: 4)
    - Memoranda. (Folder 46: 5-6)
      Includes memoranda on the situation of Czechoslovak refugees in different countries and the necessity to amend the Displaced Persons Act
    - Minutes (Folder 46: 7)
    - Notes by Slávik (Folder 46: 8)
    - Publications
      - Hlas Československa (Folder 46: 9)
      - Zpravodaj Rady Svobodného Československa (Folder 46: 10)
      - Zprávy (Box-folder 47: 1)
    - Reports by Slávik and others (Folder 47: 2)
    - Statutes (Folder 47: 3)
    - Subject file
      - Displaced Persons Act., See also Correspondence/Československý Pomocný Výbor (Folder 47: 4)
        Includes correspondence with the United States Department of State regarding the amendment of the act.
      - Forced labor (Folder 47: 5)
    - Miscellaneous materials and clippings (Folder 47: 6)
  - Member, Assembly of Captive European Nations (ACEN), 1954? (Folder 47: 7)
- Československá Obec Sokolská (Czechoslovak Sokols) File, 1939-1968. (Box 47-48)
  Articles, brochures, clippings, correspondence, memoranda, minutes, organizational records, programs, speeches, printed matter, and miscellany, relating to Slávik's role as vice-president of the Sokols, arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - Correspondence (Folder 47: 8)
  - Minutes (Box-folder 48: 1)
  - Publications (Folder 48: 2-3)
  - Speeches (Folder 48: 4-6)
  - Statutes (Folder 48: 7)
- Subject File, 1918-1968. (Box 48-51)
  Articles, brochures, clippings, comments, maps, organizational records, press releases, programs, proposals, reports, speeches, writings, printed matter, and miscellany relating to various persons, organizations and countries, arranged alphabetically by subject. See also Career file.
  - American Relief for Czechoslovakia, Inc. (Folder 48: 8)
  - Beneš, Edvard (Folder 48: 9)
  - Československá společnost (Box-folder 49: 1)
  - Československá státní škola (Folder 49: 2)
  - Československá Živnostensko-Obchodnická Strana Středostavovská v Exilu (Czechoslovak Party of Middle Classes in Exile) (Folder 49: 3)
  - Československý Pomocný Výbor (Czechoslovak Relief Committee in Austria) (Folder 49: 4)
  - Council of the Anglo-Czechoslovak Christian Fellowship (Folder 49: 5)
  - Czechoslovak National Committee, Paris (Folder 49: 6)
  - Czechoslovak National Council of America (Československá Národní Rada v Americe) (Folder 49: 7)
  - Czechoslovak National Socialist Party (Folder 49: 8)
  - Czechoslovak-Polish Confederation (Proposed) (Folder 49: 9)
  - Czechoslovak Red Cross (Folder 49: 10)
  - Czechoslovakia
    - General (Folder 49: 11)
    - Foreign relations
      - Germany (Folder 49: 12)
      - Poland (Folder 49: 13)
    - History
      - 1918-1938 (Folder 49: 14)
      - 1938-1945 (Folder 49: 15-16)
      - 1945-1992. (Box-folder 50: 1)
        Includes information by Antonin Jandáček on the February 1948 coup d'état in Czechoslovakia
    - Politics and government (Folder 50: 2)
  - Czechoslovakia. Československá tisková kancelář (New York) - Zprávy Československé Tiskové Kanceláře (Folder 50: 3)
  - Eastern Conference of the Slovak Lutheran Synod Zion (Folder 50: 4)
  - Europe, Central (Folder 50: 5)
  - European Movement Conference on Central and Eastern Europe. (Folder 50: 6)
    Includes a report by the Polish Political Council entitled "Sovietization of Polish Culture"
  - Fabry, Vladimír (Folder 50: 7)
  - Germany - Foreign relations - Czechoslovakia., See Czechoslovakia - Foreign relations - Germany
  - The Honourable Society of Cymmrodorion, London, 1941 (Folder 50: 8)
  - Hungarian News Survey (Folder 50: 9)
  - International P.E.N. Club. Center for Writers in Exile, New York (Folder 50: 10)
  - Junák (Folder 50: 11)
  - Klub Strany Lidovej Jednoty (Folder 50: 12)
  - League for Industrial Democracy (Folder 50: 13)
  - Masaryk, T. G. (Tomas Garrigue) (Folder 50: 14)
  - Munzer (Folder 50: 15)
  - Národní Rada Česká (National Czech Council) (Folder 50: 16)
  - Okánik, Ludovít (Folder 50: 17)
  - The People to People Program (Folder 50: 18)
  - Polák, Frank (Folder 50: 19)
  - Poland
    - General (Folder 50: 20)
    - Foreign relations - Czechoslovakia., See Czechoslovakia - Foreign relations - Poland
  - Raichl, Pravomil. (Folder 50: 21)
    Includes a list of prisoners in the communist concentration camps of Jachymov and Leopoldov, and a typescript entitled "The Story of Lieutenant Pravomil Raichl," relating to his escape with John Hvasta from Leopoldov
  - Ripka, Hubert (Folder 50: 22)
  - Slovakia (Folder 50: 23)
  - Společnost pro Vědy a Umění (Czechoslovak Society of Arts and Sciences in America) (Box-folder 51: 1)
  - Spolek Východoslovenských Akademikov (Folder 51: 2)
  - Štefánik, Milan (Folder 51: 3)
  - United Nations (Folder 51: 4)
  - The Woman's Club of Bloomfield (Folder 51: 5)
  - Miscellaneous (Folder 51: 6-8)
- Printed Matter, 1938-1966. (Box 51-54)
  Bulletins, clippings, newsletters, pamphlets, and miscellany, relating mainly to Czechoslovakia, arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - General - Bulletins, newsletters, pamphlets, press and publications excerpts, and miscellany (Folder 51: 9-12)
  - General - Bulletins, newsletters, pamphlets, press and publications excerpts, and miscellany (Box-folder 52: 1-5)
  - General - Bulletins, newsletters, pamphlets, press and publications excerpts, and miscellany (Box-folder 53: 1-3)
  - Clippings (Folder 53: 4-5)
  - Clippings (Box-folder 54: 1-4)
- Photographs, n.d. (Box 54 and photo file)
  226 prints depicting Juraj Slávik, his family, and other individuals on different occasions, and 5 postcards
  - 32 prints depicting Slávik, his wife and son, and other individuals on different occasions, and 5 postcards (Folder 54: 5)
  - 26 prints depicting official functions, visiting dignitaries, a girls' school, and various other aspects of Slávik's diplomatic career (Photo-file A)
  - 15 prints depicting monuments in Czechoslovakia, Slávik's visit to Cuba, and Slávik's UN appointment (Photo-file B)
  - 68 prints depicting various ceremonies in the United States and Czechoslovakia, various aspects of Slávik's career, and Slávik's family and friends (Photo-file C)
  - 84 prints depicting Slávik's family and friends, and various aspects of his career (Photo-file D)
  - 1 print of a group portrait depicting various dignitaries (Photo-file mE)
- Microfilm, 1936-1940? (Box Microfilm cabinet)
  Three reels of Slávik's memoirs "Moja pamať - živá kniha"
  - Vol. 5, 1936 - 1939 (Microfilm-cabinet 1)
  - Vol. 5, 1938 June - 1939 March (Microfilm-cabinet 2)
  - Vols. 6-7, 1939 April - 1940? June (Microfilm-cabinet 3)